<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<book lang="en">
  <title>Columba User Manual v1.0</title>

  <bookinfo>
    <corpauthor>The Columba Team</corpauthor>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>The contents of this file are subject to the Mozilla Public
      License Version 1.1 (the "License"); you may not use this file except in
      compliance with the License. You may obtain a copy of the License at
      http://www.mozilla.org/MPL/ Software distributed under the License is
      distributed on an "AS IS" basis, WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, either
      express or implied. See the License for the specific language governing
      rights and limitations under the License. The Original Code is "The
      Columba Project" The Initial Developers of the Original Code are
      Frederik Dietz and Timo Stich. Portions created by Frederik Dietz and
      Timo Stich are Copyright (C) 2003.</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </bookinfo>

  <chapter>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>Columba is an email-client written in Java, featuring a
    user-friendly graphical interface with time-saving wizards and
    internationalization support.</para>

    <para>This guide will help you to get started quickly with Columba.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Typographical conventions</title>

      <para>In this book, we'll mark some words with special
      typography:</para>

      <para><command>Commands</command> you type at the command line</para>

      <para><guilabel>Labels</guilabel> for buttons and other portions of the
      graphical interface</para>

      <para>Menu selections look like this:
      <guimenuitem>Menu</guimenuitem>-&gt;<guimenuitem>Submenu</guimenuitem>-&gt;<guimenuitem>Menu
      Item</guimenuitem></para>

      <para><prompt>Anything you type in</prompt></para>

      <para><computeroutput>Text output from a
      computer</computeroutput></para>

      <para></para>

      <para>We'll provide assorted bits of additional information in tips set
      off from the rest of the book, as well.</para>

      <para><tip>
          <para>Tips and bits of extra information will look like this.</para>
        </tip></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Additional Help Sources</title>

      <para>You will find the most up-to-date information on our website at
      <ulink url="http://columba.sf.net">http://columba.sf.net</ulink> in the
      <emphasis>Documentation</emphasis> section.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>License</title>

      <para>Columba is free software that is licensed under the <ulink
      url="http://www.mozilla.org/MPL/MPL-1.1.html">Mozilla Public
      License</ulink>. This license allows you to use, modify and redistribute
      this software. There's a nice <ulink
      url="http://www.mozilla.org/MPL/FAQ.html">FAQ</ulink> which should
      answer most of your questions. Note, that we have choosen this license
      intentially to become more business-friendly. There's no virual effect
      as seen with the GPL here.</para>

      <para>Columba is not a monolithic application. It makes use of
      dynamically loaded extensions. These extensions are what we call
      plugins. The MPL License lets you create closed-source or binary plugins
      and allows you to sell these without a problem.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Installation</title>

    <para>Download Columba from <ulink
    url="http://columba.sourceforge.net/">http://columba.sf.net</ulink> and be
    sure to read the information provided on our Download page.</para>

    <sect1>
      <title>Prerequisites</title>

      <para>Columba is written entirely in Java and therefore is platform
      independent. It runs on almost any modern personal computer. To
      successfully start and run Columba you need the following:</para>

      <para>Java Runtime Environment or Java Development Kit. JDK 1.4 or
      higher is required for Linux, Mac OS X, and Windows Platforms. Columba
      will not run with JDK 1.3 or older. We recommend to use Java 5 for
      superior performance.</para>

      <para>A computer with reasonable memory and CPU power. For memory, 512
      MB is recommended. For CPU, a Pentium III or equivalent is the
      recommended minimum.</para>

      <para>A specific operating system is not required. Columba is known to
      run on Windows 98, 2000, NT, and XP, on Linux, and MacOS X. It has been
      predominantly developed and tested on Linux (mostly Gentoo Linux and/or
      Ubuntu Linux).</para>

      <para>Download Java at: <ulink
      url="http://java.com">http://java.com</ulink></para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Windows</title>

      <para>The preferred way should be to download
      <filename>ColumbaSetup.exe</filename>. Double-click the file to start
      the setup. A wizard will guide you step-by-step throughout the
      installation process.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Linux</title>

      <para>Download the RPM (the RPM Package Manager) package of Columba. You
      have to become root user in order to be able to install Columba.
      Enter</para>

      <para><command>rpm -Uvh columba-1.0_M2-0.rpm</command></para>

      <para>in your favourite shell. This will install Columba in
      <filename>/opt/columba </filename>and will create a symbolic link in
      <filename>/usr/bin/columba</filename>.</para>

      <para>The RPM package does not have any dependency checking built-in. It
      therefor won't check if you installed a matching Java RPM.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Generic</title>

      <para>Download the binary package and extract its contents.</para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Getting Started</title>

    <para>This chapter introduces all basic concepts of Columba. It will help
    you setup an email account, checking for new mail, composing and sending a
    message.</para>

    <para>Here is a list of things that you should look up before you start
    Columba for the first time:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Your POP3 or IMAP server for incoming email, which usually is
        named similar to "pop3.yahoo.com"</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Your SMTP server for outgoing email, which usually is named
        similar to "smtp.yahoo.com"</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Your username and password for your POP3- or IMAP-account</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>You should contact your ISP (Internet Service Provider) or your
    system administrator if you do not know these settings.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Starting Columba for the First Time</title>

      <para>To start Columba do one of the following:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Select <emphasis
          role="bold"><application>Programs</application></emphasis>-&gt;<emphasis
          role="bold"><application>Columba</application></emphasis> from your
          menu panel</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Type <emphasis
          role="bold"><command>columba</command></emphasis> at the command
          line</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The first time you run the program it will create a directory
      <emphasis role="bold"><filename>.columba</filename></emphasis> in your
      home directory. Windows users can find this directory in <emphasis
      role="bold"><filename>C:\Documents and
      Settings\USER\.columba</filename></emphasis>. Just replace USER with
      your username.</para>

      <para>It will then open up a first-time wizard which will guide you in
      creating a mail account.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Command Line Options</title>

      <para>Columba has a number of command line options which come in handy
      you. You can find the full list by running <emphasis
      role="bold"><command>columba -help</command></emphasis>.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>To start Columba and begin composing a message to a email
          address: <emphasis role="bold"><command>columba --mailurl
          peter@somewhere.com</command></emphasis></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>To make your web browser use Columba as default email client,
          enter <emphasis role="bold">c<command>olumba --mailurl
          %s</command></emphasis> as the email handler in your web browser.
          When using the windows installer you do not have to do this
          manually. Columba will automatically ask you if you want it to make
          it the system default email client.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Setting Up Your Account</title>

      <para>Setting up your account involves several steps:<orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Entering your identity including name and email
            address</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Configuring your incoming mail server</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Specifying your outgoing mail server</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist></para>

      <figure>
        <title>Identity Information</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/wizard_account_identity.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Name:</emphasis></para>

      <para>This is the real name assigned to this identity - generally your
      first and a last name. The text you enter here is included in the From:
      field of all your outgoing messages.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Address:</emphasis></para>

      <para>Specify your email address here.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Account Name:</emphasis></para>

      <para>Choose a name for this new account. When using multiple accounts
      this will help you distinguishing them from each other.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Incoming Server Properties</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/wizard_account_incoming.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Login:</emphasis></para>

      <para>This is the name you use to log on to this email account. For
      example, in the upcoming mail account donald@mail.com, the login name is
      donald. This is a very common scheme used by most providers. Check with
      your Internet Service Provider if you are not sure what your login name
      is.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Host:</emphasis></para>

      <para>Name of your incoming mail server.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Type:</emphasis></para>

      <para>This indicates the email protocol this incoming email server uses:
      POP3 or IMAP. If you are not sure which to use, ask your administrator.
      In most cases it is POP3.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Outgoing Server Properties</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/wizard_account_outgoing.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Host:</emphasis></para>

      <para>Name of your outgoing mail server.</para>

      <para>You are now ready to work with Columba!</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Receiving Messages</title>

      <para>To check your email, press the <emphasis
      role="bold"><guibutton>Receive/Send</guibutton></emphasis> toolbar
      button or the <emphasis role="bold">F9</emphasis> Function Key. If this
      is the first time you are checking mail, or you have not asked Columba
      to save your password, you will be prompted for the password. Enter your
      password and your email will be downloaded.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Mail Toolbar</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/toolbar_main.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Sending Messages</title>

      <para>Click the New Message item in the menu Message to open the
      composer window. Alternatively you can use the <emphasis
      role="bold"><guibutton>New Message</guibutton></emphasis> button in the
      toolbar.</para>

      <para>While online, after composing your message press the <emphasis
      role="bold"><guibutton>Send Now</guibutton></emphasis> button or
      alternatively select <emphasis
      role="bold"><guimenuitem>File</guimenuitem>-&gt;<guimenuitem>Send
      Message</guimenuitem></emphasis>. If you are not online, select
      <emphasis
      role="bold"><guimenuitem>File</guimenuitem>-&gt;<guimenuitem>Send
      Later</guimenuitem></emphasis></para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Using Columba</title>

    <para></para>

    <figure>
      <title>Main Window of Columba</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/frame_mail_with_shadow_resized_notes.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Folder Tree:</emphasis></para>

    <para>New messages can be found in the <emphasis
    role="bold">Inbox</emphasis> folder. The Inbox label will be bold when the
    mailbox contains recent messages. The number in the brackets reflects the
    total number of unread messages. When moving the mouse cursor above the
    mailbox a tooltip with additional information appears.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Message List:</emphasis></para>

    <figure>
      <title>Message List</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/table_attachment.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>New messages in the message list view are marked in bold. A little
    envelope symbol in the first column shows if the message has already been
    read (has "<emphasis role="bold">open</emphasis>" envelope) or not (has
    "closed" envelope). When selecting a message in the message list, it will
    automatically be shown in the message view. If the message has an
    attachment, it will have a little paperclip icon in the second
    column.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Message Viewer:</emphasis></para>

    <para>The message view shows the header of all messages, with the most
    important information listed first: Subject, Sender, Date and From.The
    message body text follows with the message signature underneath. If the
    message contains attachments a paperclip symbol in the message header
    notifies the user.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Attachment Viewer:</emphasis></para>

    <para>The attachment viewer lets you select attachments to individually
    open, view or save to files with the context menu.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Reading Mail</title>

      <para>Start reading messages by selecting a mail folder in the tree
      view. To read a message select it in the message list; if you would like
      to see it in its own window, double-click it.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Reading Mail with the Keyboard</title>

        <para>You can navigate the message list by pressing the arrow keys up
        and down. To jump to the next unread message press <emphasis
        role="bold">n</emphasis>. You can go to the previous unread message by
        pressing <emphasis role="bold">p</emphasis>.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Sorting the Message List</title>

        <figure>
          <title>Table View</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/table.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>Columba helps your organise your messages by letting you sort
        your email. To sort by sender, subject or date, click on the buttons
        with those labels on top of the message list. The direction of the
        arrow next to the label indicates the direction of the sort, and if
        you click again, you will sort them in the reverse order.<emphasis
        role="bold"></emphasis> <tip>
            <para>To look at the complete headers for email messages, select
            <emphasis
            role="bold"><guimenuitem>View</guimenuitem>-&gt;<guimenuitem>Message
            Display</guimenuitem>-&gt;<guimenuitem>Show Full
            Headers</guimenuitem></emphasis>. To see absolutely every bit,
            choose <emphasis
            role="bold"><guimenuitem>View</guimenuitem>-&gt;<guimenuitem>Show
            Message Source</guimenuitem></emphasis>.</para>
          </tip></para>

        <para>You can also choose a threaded message view. <emphasis
        role="bold">Select View-&gt;Threaded View</emphasis> to turn the
        threaded view on and off. When you select this option, Columba groups
        the replies to a message with the original so you can follow the
        thread of conversation.</para>

        <para><figure>
            <title>Threaded View</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/table2.jpg" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Filtering the Message List</title>

        <para><figure>
            <title>Filter Toolbar</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/toolbar_filter_new2.png" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure></para>

        <para>To show new messages only:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select the left-most read message button</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>To show only new messages from donald@duck.com:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Enter "donald@duck.com" in the textfield and press
            Enter</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>All filter operations can be easily combined in this way. To
        view all messages again, press the <emphasis
        role="bold"><guibutton>Clear</guibutton></emphasis> button.<emphasis
        role="bold"></emphasis> <tip>
            <para>Pressing the <emphasis
            role="bold"><guibutton>Advanced..</guibutton></emphasis> button
            will open a search dialog, with the currently viewed folder
            already selected for you.</para>
          </tip></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Deleting your Mail</title>

        <para>Once you have read your mail, you may want to get rid of it. To
        delete a message:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select the message(s), you want to delete</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Select <emphasis
            role="bold"><guimenuitem>Messages</guimenuitem>-&gt;<guimenuitem>Delete
            Messages</guimenuitem></emphasis>, or right click on the message
            and select <emphasis role="bold"><guimenuitem>Delete
            Messages</guimenuitem> <emphasis>or hit the</emphasis>
            Delete<emphasis> key. </emphasis></emphasis></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para><tip>
            <para>Selecting more messages at once:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Hold down the Shift key to select a range of messages
                you want to delete</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Hold down the Ctrl key to select multiple messages
                individually</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </tip></para>

        <tip>
          <para>Use the <guibutton>Delete</guibutton> button in the
          toolbar!</para>
        </tip>

        <figure>
          <title>Toolbar</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/toolbar_main.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>This does not delete your messages immediately. Instead it moves
        messages to the Trash folder.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Saving or Opening attachments</title>

        <para>If you get an attachment with your email message, Columba can
        help you save or open it with the appropriate application.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Attachment Viewer</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/panel_attachments.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>To save an attachment to disk:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Right-click the attachment icon and select <emphasis
            role="bold"><guimenuitem>Save As..</guimenuitem></emphasis></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Choose a location and a name for the file</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>click <emphasis role="bold">OK</emphasis></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>To open an attachment in a program:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Open the mail message with the attachment you want to
            read</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Right-click the attachment icon and Select <emphasis
            role="bold"><guimenuitem>Open
            With...</guimenuitem></emphasis></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Select the program you would like to use. It will start up
            and open the document.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <tip>
          <para>Double-clicking the attachment icon will open the attachment
          with the previously chosen program.</para>
        </tip>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Checking for New Mail</title>

      <para></para>

      <figure>
        <title>File Menu</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/menu_file.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Use the <emphasis role="bold">Get New Messages</emphasis> or the
      <emphasis role="bold">Get New Messages for...</emphasis> items in the
      File menu to individually download new messages from one account or from
      all accounts at once. To automatically send and receive all messages
      press the <emphasis role="bold">Receive and Send</emphasis> button in
      the toolbar.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Composing New Email Messages</title>

      <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Message-&gt;New Message</emphasis> or
      hit <emphasis role="bold">Ctrl-M</emphasis> to open the composer window.
      Alternatively you can use the <emphasis role="bold">New Message
      button</emphasis> in the toolbar.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Composing a Message</title>

      <para><figure>
          <title>Composer Window</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/frame_composer_small_notes.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure></para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Enter the person you want to send a message to in the upper
          left corner textfield. Press the TAB button to automatically jump to
          the Subject textfield.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Enter the subject you want. This is the first line the person
          will read, so it should be pretty clear and descriptive in order to
          allow the person to categorize the message. Remember also that a lot
          of people use the subject field to decide on what messages might be
          spam. Sending a message with a subject "Hello!" to someone who might
          not recognise your email address is a sure way to get your message
          deleted without even being read. Pressing TAB again will show the
          prompt in the message body textfield.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>This is where you write your message. Note: You can quickly
          choose your preferred account and the message priority by using
          controls in the middle of the composer dialog.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>Once you have written your message, click the <emphasis
      role="bold"><guiicon>Send Now</guiicon></emphasis> button or select
      <emphasis
      role="bold"><guimenuitem>File</guimenuitem>-&gt;<guimenuitem>Send
      Now</guimenuitem></emphasis> or press <emphasis
      role="bold">Ctrl-Enter</emphasis> if you are online or select <emphasis
      role="bold"><guimenuitem>File</guimenuitem>-&gt;<guimenuitem>Send</guimenuitem>
      <guimenuitem>Later</guimenuitem></emphasis> if you are offline.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Composer Toolbar</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/toolbar_composer.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Sending Composed Messages Later</title>

      <para>Columba will normally send mail as soon as you click the <emphasis
      role="bold"><guimenuitem>Send</guimenuitem></emphasis>
      <guimenuitem>Later</guimenuitem> button. However, there are a few ways
      you can save a message to be sent later:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>If you are <emphasis role="bold">offline</emphasis>, Columba
          will add your messages to the Outbox queue. The next time you are
          online and send or receive mail, that message will be sent when you
          select <emphasis
          role="bold"><guimenuitem>File</guimenuitem>-&gt;<guimenuitem>Send
          Unsent Messages</guimenuitem></emphasis> or click the <emphasis
          role="bold">F10</emphasis> function key. It will not be sent as part
          of a normal <emphasis
          role="bold"><guimenuitem>File</guimenuitem>-&gt;<guimenuitem>Receive
          and Send</guimenuitem></emphasis> selection or by pressing the
          <emphasis role="bold">F9</emphasis> function key.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Choose <emphasis
          role="bold"><guimenuitem>File</guimenuitem>-&gt;<guimenuitem>Save As
          Draft</guimenuitem></emphasis> to store your messages in the draft
          folder</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Adding Attachments</title>

      <para>To attach a file to your message:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Press the <emphasis role="bold">Attach File </emphasis>button
          on the composer toolbar or select <emphasis
          role="bold"><guimenuitem>Message</guimenuitem>-&gt;<guimenuitem>Attach
          File</guimenuitem></emphasis> or press <emphasis
          role="bold">Ctrl-Alt-A</emphasis> key combination.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Select the file you want to attach using the dialog box that
          is displayed.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Press <emphasis role="bold">OK</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <tip>
        <para>You can add multiple attachments at once.</para>

        <para>When you send the message, a copy of the attachment will go with
        it. Be aware that it may take a while depending on the current speed
        of your internet connection to send large attachments. Remember also
        that the attachment(s) will be sent to all recipients so if you do not
        want some to receive it, you will have to do transactions.</para>
      </tip>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Specifying Recipients for Email</title>

      <figure>
        <title>Recipients List</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/composer_recipients.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Like most email programs, Columba recognizes three types of
      addresses: Primary recipients, secondary recipients and hidden ("blind")
      recipients.</para>

      <para>The simplest way to direct a message is to put the address in the
      <emphasis role="bold">To:</emphasis> field, which denotes primary
      recipients. To send a message to more than one or two people, use the
      <emphasis role="bold">Cc:</emphasis> field.</para>

      <para>"Cc" stands for "Carbon Copy" (if you need further explanation,
      ask someone familiar with typewriters!). Use it whenever you want to
      share a message you have written with someone else.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Bcc:</emphasis> (Blind Carbon Copy) is a
      little bit more complex. You use it like <emphasis
      role="bold">Cc:</emphasis>, but people on the <emphasis
      role="bold">Bcc:</emphasis> list are hidden from the other recipients of
      the message. Use it to send a mail to a large group of people,
      especially if they don't know each other, privacy is a concern or you
      are sharing a secrets.</para>

      <tip>
        <para>In these days where Spam is more prevalent than real Email, it
        is a very good idea to use Bcc instead of Cc whenever possible. There
        are an increasing number of viruses and other internet nasties that
        are very capable of scanning all of your stored messages for new
        addresses and then forwarding these addresses on for sending further
        spam.</para>

        <para>Now you might be very internet savy and have defenses against
        such problems but do all the people you correspond with? It only takes
        one message on an insecure machine and you have inadvertantly become
        part of the problem.</para>

        <para>When using Bcc, the recipient of the message only sees your
        email address and his own because the email server creates a new
        message for each email address in your Bcc list. Email is for
        commmunication, not to show how many people you know!</para>
      </tip>

      <para>If you frequently write mail to the same group of people, you can
      create address lists in the addressbook, and then send them mail as
      though they had a single address.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Address Auto-completion</title>

      <para>Columba automatically saves address in its Collect Addresses book.
      When entering addresses it will offer a drop down list of possible
      address completions from your addressbooks and the Collected
      Addresses.<tip>
          <para>You can also enter nicknames, here.</para>
        </tip></para>

      <para>Alternatively you can click on the <emphasis role="bold">contact
      button</emphasis> (the one that looks like a small photo ID) in the
      composer toolbar to open a dialog, to get you a list of the email
      addresses in your addressbook. Select addresses and click the arrows to
      move the addresses into the appropriate address columns.<tip>
          <para>You can use drag and drop in the dialog, to create the
          recipients list.</para>
        </tip></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Replying to Email Messages</title>

      <para>To reply to an email press the <emphasis role="bold">Reply
      button</emphasis>, or select <emphasis role="bold">Message-&gt;Reply to
      Message</emphasis> alternatively. That will open the message composer.
      The <emphasis role="bold">To:</emphasis> and <emphasis
      role="bold">Subject:</emphasis> fields are already filled, although you
      can change them if you wish. In addition the full text of the old
      message is inserted into the new message, with a "&gt;" character in
      front of each line. This should indicate that its part of the previous
      message.</para>

      <para>If you are reading a message with several recipients you might
      want to use <emphasis role="bold">Message-&gt;Reply to All</emphasis>
      instead.</para>

      <tip>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Message-&gt;Reply to
        Mailinglist</emphasis> tries to determine the list name for you. This
        is the preferred way of replying when participating in mailing
        lists.</para>
      </tip>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Forwarding Mail</title>

      <para>Forwarding mail is particularly useful if you have received a
      message and you think someone else would like to see it. You can forward
      a message as an attachment by selecting <emphasis
      role="bold">Message-&gt;Forward as Attachment</emphasis>, or you can
      send it inline as a quoted portion of the message you are
      sending.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Using Multiple Accounts</title>

      <para><emphasis>add treeview picture here </emphasis></para>

      <para>Every account shares the same Inbox mailfolder for receiving
      messages. You can change the default behaviour in the account
      preferences dialog under the Special Folders Tab. This enables you to
      use different mailfolders for each account and makes using multiple
      accounts more convenient.</para>

      <para><figure>
          <title>Receive Message Menu</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/menu_file.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure></para>

      <para>When using <emphasis role="bold">File-&gt;Get New Messages
      for</emphasis>, you can choose which account you want to check.
      Selecting <emphasis role="bold">File-&gt;Get New Messages</emphasis>
      item (or by pressing <emphasis role="bold">Ctrl-T</emphasis>) makes it
      easy to check for new messages in all accounts simultaneously.</para>

      <para><figure>
          <title>Identity Panel in Composer</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/composer_identity_panel.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure></para>

      <para>The composer lets you choose the outgoing mailserver. When
      replying to messages, Columba automatically tries to guess the correct
      account for you. You can choose one account to be your default account.
      This is the account Columba chooses when it cannot determine the correct
      account and it is also the default account when opening a new composer
      window.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Organizing and Managing your Email</title>

    <para></para>

    <section>
      <title>Importing Your Old Email</title>

      <para>Columba allows you to import old email and data, so that you do
      not have to worry about losing your old information.</para>

      <para>Columba can import the following types of data:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Mbox (mbox) - The email format used by most email clients. One
          single file containing a complete mail folder</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>MH style mailbox (mh) - A folder containing a single file for
          every message</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Mozilla (mbox)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Evolution (mbox)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Pegasus Mail (mbox)</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <tip>
        <para>Visit our website at <ulink
        url="http://columba.sourceforge.net/"></ulink> to get the most
        up-to-date information about importing data in Columba.</para>
      </tip>

      <para>To import your old email:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Utilities-&gt;Import
          Mailbox...</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Choose the email format, click <emphasis
          role="bold">Next</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Choose the file and the destination folder in Columba, click
          <emphasis role="bold">Next</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Finish</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para><figure>
          <title>Mail Import Wizard</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/wizard_import.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Getting Organized with Folders</title>

      <para>Columba keeps mail in folders. You start out with a few mail
      folders, such as Inbox, Outbox, Drafts, Templates, Sent and Trash, but
      you can create as many as you like.</para>

      <para>Create new folders by selecting <emphasis
      role="bold">Folder-&gt;Create new Subfolder...</emphasis> Columba will
      ask you for the name and type of your new folder, and will provide you
      with a folder tree so you can pick where it goes.</para>

      <para>When you click OK, your new folder will appear in the folder view.
      You can cut/copy/paste messages between your folders. Alternatively you
      can use the <emphasis role="bold">Move Messages button</emphasis> or
      <emphasis role="bold">Copy Messages button</emphasis> in the toolbar.
      <figure>
          <title>Toolbar</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/toolbar_main.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure></para>

      <tip>
        <para>You can also use drag and drop to copy/move messages between
        folders.</para>
      </tip>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Create Filter Rules to Automatically Organize Mail</title>

      <para></para>

      <figure>
        <title>FilterList Dialog</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/dialog_filterlist.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>It is important to note that filters are attached to folders and
      only act on a specific folder. Firstly, select the folder you wish to
      attach a filter to (most commonly <emphasis
      role="bold">Inbox</emphasis>). You then open the filter dialog by
      clicking <emphasis role="bold">Folder-&gt;Message Filters..</emphasis>
      This enables you to manage all filters of this folder. You can easily
      (de)activate filters individually by selecting the checkbox in the
      column <emphasis role="bold">Enabled</emphasis>.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Add: </emphasis></para>

      <para>This creates a new filter and automatically opens a new <emphasis
      role="bold">Filter Options Dialog</emphasis> to let you edit the filter
      properties.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Edit:</emphasis></para>

      <para>This opens the <emphasis role="bold">Filter Options
      Dialog</emphasis> to edit your filter properties.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Remove:</emphasis></para>

      <para>Deletes the selected filter.</para>

      <tip>
        <para>When opening multiple <emphasis role="bold">Filter
        Dialogs</emphasis> you can drag and drop filters between
        folders.Filters are executed in the order specified by this
        dialog.</para>

        <para>Use the <emphasis role="bold">Up</emphasis> and <emphasis
        role="bold">Down</emphasis> buttons to change the order.</para>
      </tip>

      <figure>
        <title>Filter Options Dialog</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/dialog_filter.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>This dialog lets you change filter properties. You can open it
      when selecting a filter and pressing the <emphasis role="bold">Edit
      button</emphasis>. The upper panel lets you add/edit/remove filter
      criteria. The lower panel enables you to edit filter actions:</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Filter description:</emphasis></para>

      <para>Specify a descriptive name for your filter.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Apply Action when..:</emphasis></para>

      <para>If you have more than one filter criteria you can choose in this
      checkbox if all or only one criteria needs to match to start the filter
      action.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Available Filters</emphasis></para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Subject - The subject line of the message.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>From - From headerfield should contain/not contain specified
          string.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>To - To headerfield should contain/not contain specified
          string.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Cc - Cc headerfield should contain/not contain specified
          string.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Bcc - Bcc headerfield should contain/not contain specified
          string.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Custom Headerfield - The filter can look at any header you
          want, even custom ones. Enter the headerfield name in the first
          textbox and the search text in the second one.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Body - search in the actual text of the message.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Date - Filter message according to the date which they were
          sent: First, choose the conditions you want a message to meet -
          before a given time, or after it. Then choose the date.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Flag - First choose a flag, which can be Seen, Expunged,
          Flagged, etc. Choose a condition afterwards.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Priority - Choose between Highest, High, Normal, Low,
          Lowest<emphasis></emphasis></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Size - Filter messages based on the size of the message in Kb
          (Kilobytes).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Color - Filter messages based on color flag</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Account - Account-based filtering</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Sender is in Addressbook - check if message sender is in
          addressbook</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Match All - Match all messages automatically. Can be used to
          execute actions on every message of a folder repetitive.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Available Filter Actions:</emphasis></para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Move Message - Move message to specified destination
          folder</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Copy Message - Copy message to specified destination
          folder</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Mark as Read - Mark message as Read/Flagged/Expunged</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Delete Message - Delete message</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Color Message - Assign color to message</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Score Message - Spam filter analyzes the message, generates a
          scoring value and marks the message as either spam or non
          spam</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Using Virtual Folders</title>

      <figure>
        <title>Tree View</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/tree.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>If filters are not flexible enough for you, consider the use of
      vFolders (virtual folders). If you find yourself performing the same
      search again and again then read on.</para>

      <para>Explaining what a vFolder does is not easy at all. It looks like a
      folder, it acts like a search, and you set it up like a filter. In other
      words, while a traditional folder actually contains messages, a vFolder
      is a view of messages that may be in several different folders. The
      messages it contains are determined on the fly, when the user selects a
      vFolder, using a set of filter criteria you specified before.</para>

      <para>It is important to note that when you delete a message in a
      vFolder, Columba will automatically remove the message from the message
      list and from the folder it actually exists in.</para>

      <para>Imagine a university with overlapping and changing groups of
      faculty, staff, administrators and students. In this situation vFolders
      often make for a better organization because they can accept overlapping
      groups in a way that regular folders and file systems cannot.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Configuring Columba</title>

    <para>This chapter describes in detail all available configuration options
    of Columba, being it account configuration, mail options or general
    Columba-wide settings like fonts or proxy settings.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Configuring Accounts</title>

      <para></para>

      <figure>
        <title>Accountlist Dialog</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/dialog_accountlist.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Select <emphasis role="bold">Edit</emphasis>-&gt;<emphasis
      role="bold">Mail Account Settings...</emphasis> to open the account
      preferences dialog.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Add:</emphasis></para>

      <para>Selection Add opens the account wizard which will help you
      creating a new account.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Edit:</emphasis></para>

      <para>Lets you edit the account options.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Remove:</emphasis></para>

      <para>Deletes the currently selected account.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Identity Page</title>

        <para></para>

        <figure>
          <title>Identity Page</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/dialog_account_identity.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Account name:</emphasis></para>

        <para>Choose a name for this new account. When using multiple accounts
        this will help you distinguishing them from each other.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Make this my default
        account:</emphasis></para>

        <para>You can declare one account to be your default account. When
        using multiple accounts, the default account will have higher priority
        in any tasks.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Your Name:</emphasis></para>

        <para>This is the real name assigned to this account, generally your
        first and last name. The text you enter here, is visible in the From:
        headerfield of all your outgoing messages.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Email-Address:</emphasis></para>

        <para>Specify your email address here.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Organisation:</emphasis></para>

        <para>Your organisation will be visible in the X-Organisation:
        headerfield of all your outgoing messages. Most private individuals do
        not use this and leave it blank.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Reply-To Address:</emphasis></para>

        <para>This is the return email address used in outgoing messages and
        recipients replies, if this address is different from your email
        address specified above.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Attach this signature:</emphasis></para>

        <para>If checked this lets you choose a textfile, which is always
        appended to all composed messages. Its the perfect place to easily
        attach an electronic version of your business cards.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Incoming Server Page</title>

        <para></para>

        <figure>
          <title>Incoming Server Page</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/dialog_account_incoming.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Login:</emphasis></para>

        <para>This is the name you use to login to this email account. For
        example, in the upcoming mail account donald@mail.com, the login name
        is donald. This is a very common scheme used by most providers. Check
        with your Internet Service Provider if you are not sure what your
        login name is.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Host:</emphasis></para>

        <para>Name of your incoming mail server.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Port:</emphasis></para>

        <para>This is the port number Columba uses to connect to your mail
        server. Usually you do not need to change this option.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Authentication Type:</emphasis></para>

        <para>Depending on your mail server type, you have the choice between
        more or less secure authentication mechanisms. Most mail servers
        should work out-of-box with the default setup. But sometimes you need
        to manually choose a login method in order to make it work.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Use SSL for secure
        connections:</emphasis></para>

        <para>Use SSL (Secure Socket Layer) for server authentication and mail
        transfer security by having Columba automatically invoke the STARTTLS
        command method to start SSL. If your server does not support SSL, mail
        transfer will occur successfully, but will not be secured with
        SSL.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Store password in configuration
        file:</emphasis></para>

        <para>If you select this options, your password is remembered even if
        you quit and restart Columba so you should never be prompted to enter
        it again. If this option is turned off, you must enter your password
        each time connecting with your mail server. Select this option only if
        your PC is in a secure place.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Receiving Options Page</title>

        <para></para>

        <figure>
          <title>Receiving Options Page</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/dialog_account_receive.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Enable interval message
        checking:</emphasis></para>

        <para>Enables interval message checking, meaning Columba automatically
        checks if new messages are available in background.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Automatically download new
        messages:</emphasis></para>

        <para>If Columba found new messages, should it download them
        automatically for you?</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Play sound when new messages
        arrive:</emphasis></para>

        <para>Play a sound when a new message arrives.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Check for new messages every xxx
        minutes:</emphasis></para>

        <para>Specify the interval Columba should try to check for new
        messages. Some mail servers only allow mail-checking every 10 minutes
        or even longer delays. You should set this value to at least this
        minimum value.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Leave Messages on server (POP3
        only):</emphasis></para>

        <para>If you select this options, Columba copies the message to your
        PC and leaves them on the mail server. If this is turned off, Columba
        transfers incoming messages to your PC and deletes them from your POP3
        server. Most servers allow you to indicate whether to leave the
        messages on the server so you can retrieve it from several different
        computers at various times.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Remove messages from server after xxx days
        (POP3 only):</emphasis></para>

        <para>Columba automatically deletes all messages older than xxx days
        from your POP3 server.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Exclude from fetch all (POP3
        only):</emphasis></para>

        <para>Selecting this option excludes your account from the mail check
        which is generally executed for all accounts when using the <emphasis
        role="bold">Receive and Send Messages</emphasis> action.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Receive and Send Action</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/toolbar_main.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Limit message download to ~KB (POP3
        only):</emphasis></para>

        <para>If you select this option, messages over the specified size are
        not downloaded. This can be useful on slow connections.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Automatically apply Filters on Inbox (IMAP
        only):</emphasis></para>

        <para>If you select this option, filters of your IMAP folder are
        applied automatically when selecting the folder.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Outgoing Server Page</title>

        <para></para>

        <figure>
          <title>Outgoing Server Page</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/dialog_account_outgoing.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Login:</emphasis></para>

        <para>This is the name you use to login to this email account. For
        example, in the upcoming mail account donald@mail.com, the login name
        is donald. This is a very common scheme used by most providers. Check
        with your Internet Service Provider if you are not sure what your
        login name is.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Host:</emphasis></para>

        <para>Name of your outgoing mail server.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Port:</emphasis></para>

        <para>This is the port number Columba uses to connect to your mail
        server. Usually you do not need to change this option.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Authentication Type:</emphasis></para>

        <para>You have the choice between more or less secure authentication
        mechanisms. Most mail servers should work out-of-the-box with the
        default setup. But sometimes you need to manually choose a login
        method in order to make it work. Use the <guibutton>Check Supported
        Types</guibutton> button to receive a list of all available types from
        your server.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Use SSL for secure
        connection:</emphasis></para>

        <para>Use SSL (Secure Socket Layer) for server authentication and mail
        transfer security by having Columba automatically invoke the STARTTLS
        command method to start SSL. If your server does not support SSL, mail
        transfer will occur successfully, but will not be secured with
        SSL.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Store Password in configuration
        file:</emphasis></para>

        <para>If you select this options, your password is remembered even if
        you quit and restart Columba so you should never be prompted to enter
        it again. If this option is turned off, you must enter your password
        each time connecting with your mail server. Select this option only if
        your PC is in a secure place.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Security Page</title>

        <para></para>

        <figure>
          <title>Security Page</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/dialog_account_security.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>This lets you choose whether you want to use strong encryption
        with the OpenPGP-compatible open-source software <ulink
        url="http://www.gnupg.org/">GnuPG</ulink>.</para>

        <para>You need to specify at least your PGP user-id, generally your
        email address is sufficient.<emphasis role="bold"></emphasis> <tip>
            <para>You can choose one account to be the default account in the
            Identity Tab or in the Account Preferences dialog. Other accounts
            can use the setup of the default account for themselves. So, its
            easy to specify another account which uses the same POP3
            mailserver, but not another SMTP server. You just need to select
            the <emphasis role="bold">use default account
            preferences</emphasis> checkbox to make it work.</para>
          </tip></para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Mail Options Dialog</title>

      <figure>
        <title>Mail Options Dialog</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/dialog_mail_options.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Prefer HTML messages, if
      available:</emphasis></para>

      <para>If this option is selected, Columba shows the HTML part of a
      message, if it has been sent in both formats. This is called <emphasis
      role="bold">multipart/alternative</emphasis> messages. Basically
      messages which are send in two different formats at once, plain text or
      html. If unchecked, the plain text version is displayed. Note that many
      people will not open HTML messages as it is a favourite tool of spammers
      / virus writers. It is also often used with embedded graphics / hidden
      links to track when you actually displayed the message. While HTML can
      make a message more "pretty", it adds (sometimes greatly) to the size of
      the message and is considered by most security savvy users to be too
      great a security risk.</para>

      <tip>
        <para>The attachment viewer lets you view the alternative
        format.</para>
      </tip>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Strip HTML messages:</emphasis></para>

      <para>HTML message text will transformed to plain text automatically
      before viewing.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Display emoticons as
      graphics:</emphasis></para>

      <para>Selecting this options makes the message viewer replace ASCII art
      with graphics.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Show attachments inline:</emphasis></para>

      <para>If selected, the message viewer will show all attachments inline
      automatically. This is especially useful when reading messages
      containing lots of images attached.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Use System Default Browser</emphasis></para>

      <para>Replaces the Java HTML viewer with your System's default web
      browser. This is in most cases either Internet Explorer or <ulink
      url="http://www.mozilla.org/products/firefox/">Firefox</ulink>. In
      version 1.0 we had to disable support for this feature due to technical
      reasons.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Mark messages as read after ~
      seconds:</emphasis></para>

      <para>If this option is selected, Columba automatically marks a message
      as read after it was viewed by you. Specifying a interval of 0 seconds,
      immediately marks the message read.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Ask when sending messages with empty
      subject:</emphasis></para>

      <para>When composing messages with an empty Subject: headerfield, you
      will be asked to enter a subject. If this option is not selected,
      Columba just sends the message with an empty subject. Be aware though
      that messages with blank subject fields are often deleted as spam by
      some people / filters (and even when the email address of the sender is
      known).</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Send HTML messages with alternative text
      part:</emphasis></para>

      <para>If this option is selected, HTML messages will be send in text
      plain and in HTML format. Sometimes people can not read HTML messages,
      so sending the text plain format additionally eliminates this
      problem.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Forward messages:</emphasis></para>

      <para>Forward message as attachment, just adds the message as
      attachment. Whereas forwarding messages as quoted, lets you edit the
      quoted message bodytext.</para>

      <tip>
        <para>You can always explicitly forward a message in the format you
        like from the <emphasis role="bold">Message</emphasis> menu.</para>
      </tip>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>General Options Dialog</title>

      <figure>
        <title>General Options Dialog</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/dialog_general_options.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Language:</emphasis></para>

      <para>Lets you select a different language translation package. You can
      download many translation packages from our website. Just download the
      package of choice and save it to Columba's program folder or your
      configuration folder. Columba will automatically recognize the new
      package on restart.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Toolbar Style:</emphasis></para>

      <para>This option lets you change the style of all the toolbars in
      Columba. You can enable icons, show icons with text and choose the
      location of the text. Turning off the display of toolbar icons will
      maximize the space available for displaying messages.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Look and Feel:</emphasis></para>

      <para>You can change the way Columba looks and feels with Themes (often
      also known as skins). New themes can be downloaded from our website.
      Just download the plugin and use the Plugin Manager to install the new
      Look and Feel. Restart of Columba is required.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Overwrite Look and Feel font
      settings:</emphasis></para>

      <para>Look and Feels also choose individual fonts. This option allows
      you to change the font settings of Columba, independent from the used
      theme.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Main font:</emphasis></para>

      <para>This is the font of all the controls like menus and
      buttons.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Text font:</emphasis></para>

      <para>Font used by the message viewer and the composer. Usually this
      should be a fixed width font to allow easier editing of contents.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Extending Columba</title>

    <para>A strength of Columba is its ability to easily integrate external
    tools or plugins.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Plugin Manager</title>

      <para>The plugin manager lets you organize external plugins.<figure>
          <title>Plugin Manager</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/dialog_plugin_manager.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure></para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Install Plugin:</emphasis></para>

      <para>Selecting this button will prompt you for a plugin located on your
      PC. This will automatically install the plugin for you. Note that for
      some plugins to work correctly, it may be necessary to restart
      Columba.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Remove:</emphasis></para>

      <para>Deletes the selected plugin.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Plugin Details:</emphasis></para>

      <para>Shows detailed information about the selected plugin. This should
      be the first source of information for you.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>External Tools Manager</title>

      <para>External Tools are usually commandline tools, which are used by
      Columba or plugins to offer you certain functionality.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Info Panel</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/wizard_externaltool1.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Press the <emphasis role="bold">Next</emphasis> button to go
      on.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Description Panel</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/wizard_externaltool2.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>If you do not have this tool installed, visit the URL shown below
      the description and download the tool. Press the <emphasis
      role="bold">Next</emphasis> button to go on.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Location Panel</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/wizard_externaltool3.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Most of the time, the configuration wizard will automatically be
      able to find the tool on your PC. If not, you can use the <emphasis
      role="bold">Change</emphasis> button to do it manually.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
</book>